<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<!-- Some of the more generally applicable PIs that most I-Ds might want to use -->
<!-- Try to enforce the ID-nits conventions and DTD validity -->
<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<!-- Items used when reviewing the document -->
<?rfc comments="no" ?>
<!-- Controls display of <cref> elements -->
<?rfc inline="no" ?>
<!-- When no, put comments at end in comments section,
                                 otherwise, put inline -->
<?rfc editing="no" ?>
<!-- When yes, insert editing marks: editing marks consist of a 
                                 string such as <29> printed in the blank line at the 
                                 beginning of each paragraph of text. -->
<!-- Create Table of Contents (ToC) and set some options for it.  
         Note the ToC may be omitted for very short documents,but idnits insists on a ToC 
         if the document has more than 15 pages. -->
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocompact="yes"?>
<!-- If "yes" eliminates blank lines before main section entries. -->
<?rfc tocdepth="3"?>
<!-- Sets the number of levels of sections/subsections... in ToC -->
<!-- Choose the options for the references. 
         Some like symbolic tags in the references (and citations) and others prefer 
         numbers. The RFC Editor always uses symbolic tags.
         The tags used are the anchor attributes of the references. -->
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<!-- If "yes", causes the references to be sorted in order of tags.
                                 This doesn't have any effect unless symrefs is "yes" also. -->
<!-- These two save paper: Just setting compact to "yes" makes savings by not starting each 
         main section on a new page but does not omit the blank lines between list items. 
         If subcompact is also "yes" the blank lines between list items are also omitted. -->
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>
<!-- end of list of popular I-D processing instructions -->
<!-- end of list of processing instructions -->
<rfc category="std" docName="draft-baker-openstack-rbac-federated-identity-00"
     ipr="trust200902">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="RBAC Identity">Federated Identity for IPv6 Role-base Access
    Control</title>
    <author fullname="Fred Baker" initials="F.J." surname="Baker">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <postal>
          <street/>
          <city>Santa Barbara</city>
          <code>93117</code>
          <region>California</region>
          <country>USA</country>
        </postal>
        <email>fred@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <area>Internet Engineering Task Force</area>
    <workgroup/>
    <abstract>
      <t>This note describes an IPv6 option intended to carry a Federated
      Identity for use in Role-Based Access Control. Rather than identify a
      person, it identifies a group of systems that the sender is a member of.
      Role-Based Access Control permits specified sets of systems to
      communicate with other specified sets of systems, with the intention of
      scalability.</t>
    </abstract>
    <!--		
		<note title="Foreword">
		</note>
		-->
    <!--
      <?rfc needLines="10" ?>
      <texttable anchor="table_example" title="A Very Simple Table">
      <preamble>Tables use ttcol to define column headers and widths.
      Every cell then has a &quot;c&quot; element for its content.</preamble>
          <ttcol align="center">ttcol #1</ttcol>
                                    <ttcol align="center">ttcol #2</ttcol>
                      <c>c #1</c>		<c>c #2</c>
                      <c>c #3</c>		<c>c #4</c>
                      <c>c #5</c>		<c>c #6</c>
      <postamble>which is a very simple example.</postamble>
      </texttable>
    -->
  </front>
  <middle>
    <!--		
      <t>There are multiple list styles: "symbols", "letters", "numbers",
"hanging", "format", etc.</t>
      <t>
	<list style="symbols">
	    <t>First bullet</t>
	    <t>Second bullet</t>
	</list>
     </t>
-->
    <!--
<figure anchor="reference" title="Figure">
<artwork align="center">
<![CDATA[
	ASCII artwork goes here... 
]]>
</artwork>
</figure>
-->
    <?rfc ="5"?>
    <section title="Introduction">
      <t>In the course of developing draft-baker-ipv6-openstack-model, it was
      determined that a way was needed to encode a federated identity for use
      in Role-Based Access Control. This note describes an <xref
      target="RFC2460">IPv6</xref> option that could be carried in the
      Hop-by-Hop or Destination Options Header. The format of an option is
      defined in section 4.2 of that document, and the Hop-by-Hop and
      Destination Options are defined in sections 4.3 and 4.6 of that document
      respectively.</t>
      <t>A "Federated Identity", in the words of the Wikipedia, "is the means
      of linking an electronic identity and attributes, stored across multiple
      distinct identity management systems." In this context, it is a fairly
      weak form of that; it is intended for quick interpretation in an access
      list at the Internet layer as opposed to deep analysis for login or
      other security purposes at the application layer, and rather than
      identifying an individual or a system, it identifies a set of systems
      whose members are authorized to communicate freely among themselves and
      may also be authorized to communicate with other identified sets of
      systems. Either two systems are authorized to communicate or they are
      not, and unauthorized traffic can be summarily discarded. The identifier
      is defined in a hierarchical fashion, for flexibility and
      scalability.</t>
      <t>"Role-Based Access Control", in this context, applies to groups of
      virtual or physical hosts, not individuals. In the simplest case, the
      several tenants of a multi-tenant data center might be identified, and
      authorized to communicate only with other systems within the same
      "tenant" or with identified systems in other tenants that manage
      external access. One could imagine a company purchasing cloud services
      from multiple data center operators, and as a result wanting to identify
      the systems in its tenant in one cloud service as being authorized to
      communicate with the systems its tenant of the other. One could further
      imagine a given department within that company being authorized to speak
      only with itself and an identified set of other departments within the
      same company. To that end, when a datagram is sent, it is tagged with
      the federated identify of the sender (e.g., {datacenter, client,
      department}), and the receiving system filters traffic it receives to
      limit itself to a specific set of authorized communicants.</t>
      <!--
    <section title="Requirements Language">
      <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
      "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
      document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
      target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
    </section>
    -->
    </section>
    <section anchor="sect2" title="Federated identity Option">
      <t>The option is defined as a sequence of numbers that identify relevant
      parties hierarchically. The specific semantics (as in, what number
      identifies what party) are beyond the scope of this specification, but
      they may be interpreted as being successively more specific; as shown in
      <xref target="hierarchical"/>, the first might identify a cloud
      operator, the second, if present, might identify a client of that
      operator, and the third, if present, might identify a subset of that
      client's systems. In an application entirely used by Company A, there
      might be only one number, and it would identify sets of systems
      important to Company A such as business units. If Company A uses the
      services of a multi-tenant data center #1, it might require that there
      be two numbers, identifying Company A and its internal structure. If
      Company A uses the services of both multi-tenant data centers #1 and #2,
      and they are federated, the identifier might need to identify the data
      center, the client, and the structure of the client.</t>
      <figure anchor="hierarchical"
              title="Use case: Identifying authorized communicatants in an RBAC environment">
        <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
                   _.----------------------.
           _.----''                         `------.
      ,--''                                         `---.
   ,-' DataCenter      .---------------------.           `-.
 ,'    Company #2,---''      Unauthorized     `----.        `.
;              ,' ,-----+-----.        ,--+--------.`.        :
|             (  ( Department 1)--//--( Department 2) )       |
;              `. `-----+----+'        `-----------','        |
 `.              `----. |     X Company A     _.---'        ,'
   '-.                 A|------X------------''           ,-'
      `---.            u|       X                   _.--'
           `------.    t|        X          _.----''
                   `---h|---------X-------''
                       o|          X
                   _.--r+-----------X------.
           _.----''    i|            X      `------.
      ,--''            z|             X             `---.
   ,-' DataCenter      e|--------------X-----.           `-.
 ,'    Company #2,---''d|               X     `----.        `.
;              ,' ,-----+-----.        ,-+---------.`.        :
|             (  ( Department 1)      ( Department 2) )       |
;              `. `-----------'        `-----------','        |
 `.              `----.     Company A         _.---'        ,'
   '-.                 `--------------------''           ,-'
      `---.                                         _.--'
           `------.                         _.----''
                   `----------------------''
]]></artwork>
      </figure>
      <section anchor="format" title="Option Format">
        <t>A number (<xref target="number"/>) is represented as a base 128
        number whose coefficients are stored in the lower 7 bits of a string
        of bytes. The upper bit of each byte is zero, except in the final
        byte, in which case it is 1. The most significant coefficient of a
        non-zero number is never zero.</t>
        <figure anchor="number" title="Sample numbers">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
8 = 8*128^0
+-+------+
|1|    8 |
+-+------+

987 = 7*128^1 + 91*128^0
+-+------+-+------+
|0|    7 |1|   91 |
+-+------+-+------+

121393 = 7*128^2 + 52*128^1 + 49*128^0
+-+------+-+------+-+------+
|0|    7 |0|   52 |1|   49 |
+-+------+-+------+-+------+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <t>The identifier {8, 987, 121393} looks like</t>
        <figure anchor="identifier" title="">
          <artwork align="center"><![CDATA[
+-------+-------+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+
| type  | len=6 |1|   8 |0|   7 |1|  91 |0|   7 |0|  52 |1|  49 |
+-------+-------+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+-+-----+
]]></artwork>
        </figure>
        <section anchor="destopt"
                 title="Use in the Destination Options Header">
          <t>In an environment in which the validation of the option only
          occurs in the receiving system or its hypervisor, this option is
          best placed in the Destination Options Header.</t>
        </section>
        <section anchor="hopbyhop" title="Use in the Hop-by-Hop Header">
          <t>In an environment in which the validation of the option occurs in
          transit, such as in a firewall or other router, this option is best
          placed in the Hop-by-Hop Header.</t>
        </section>
      </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
      <t>This memo asks the IANA for no new parameters yet. It will.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
      <t>The proposed option is intended for use in a context such as
      draft-baker-ipv6-openstack-model, in which tagging of data with a group
      identity of its sender coupled with a policy that a given destination
      may only be reachable through the network for a stated set of senders,
      whether implemented at the end station or somewhere en route. It is not
      a complete security solution; if the use of TLS or other security
      apparatus would have been appropriate in its non-datacenter
      implementation, it is still appropriate. The tool presents a first-order
      removal of obvious bogons, similar to the behavior of a firewall.</t>
      <t>Some may argue that the presence of a firewall, whether implemented
      using RBAC or any other technology, fails Saltzer's <xref
      target="Saltzer">End to End Arguments in System Design</xref>. This is
      not the case, or at least not the case any worse than current Internet
      implementation does. A system that is never reachable is
      indistinguishable from one that does not exist, in the Internet. A
      correspondent may desire to reach it, but that is another matter. If the
      system were sometimes reachable, perhaps because a path sometimes went
      one way and sometimes another, that would subvert the intention of the
      endpoint, and would lead the administration to attempt to diagnose a
      fault. However, a system that is never reachable doesn't result in such
      procedures unless the administration thinks it should be reachable in
      the normal case, and a system in another network would not have such
      assumptions placed on it.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Privacy" title="Privacy Considerations">
      <t>Privacy bears especial consideration in this case, as the defined
      identifier format could obviously be used for any purpose including
      carrying an individual's Social Security Number or other identifying
      information. Doing so, however, would defeat the intended purpose, which
      is to scalably identify a group of computers that the sender of a
      message is a member of, for the purposes of Role-Based Access Control.
      <xref target="RFC6973"/> observes that <list style="empty">
          <t>"...the extent to which protocol designers can foresee all of the
          privacy implications of a particular protocol at design time is
          limited. An individual protocol may be relatively benign on its own,
          and it may make use of privacy and security features at lower layers
          of the protocol stack (Internet Protocol Security, Transport Layer
          Security, and so forth) to mitigate the risk of attack. But when
          deployed within a larger system or used in a way not envisioned at
          design time, its use may create new privacy risks."</t>
        </list></t>
      <t>In this case, the possibility is all too obvious.</t>
      <t><xref target="RFC2804"/> and <xref target="RFC7258"/> go on from
      there to note that monitoring of the Internet, whether specific to a
      warrant or pervasive, although carried out with the best of intent (in
      their own view) by IT staff, law enforcement, or intelligence agencies,
      reduces the security of the system and provides a means by which attacks
      of various kinds can be carried out. A recent example of the kinds of
      attacks that can result has involved Apple Computer, which at the time
      escrowed security keys for owners of its products. Some individuals had
      photographs stolen and published that were embarrassing to them, and
      Apple was accused of leaking the security information after being
      hacked. Apple responds that the hack, and the leak, never occurred.
      However, Apple subsequently chose to follow the advice of <xref
      target="RFC1984"/>, which was to no longer open itself to the
      possibility of such a leak by escrowing the keys.</t>
      <t>It would be a mistake to use this option to identify a person in any
      way. It would subvert the intended scalability of RBAC, and would likely
      compromise the privacy of the individual.</t>
      <t>By extension, it could be argued that an option that identifies the
      company of the sender (such as {data center operator, customer})
      simplifies traffic analysis of the sender's computers and may contribute
      to fingerprinting techniques that might further identify the computer.
      The discerning reader will note, however, that the IPv6 header already
      contains information that explicitly accomplishes that, in its source
      address.</t>
    </section>
    <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements">
      <t>The subject arose from conversations within Cisco and with a Cisco
      customer regarding the use of federated identity in an OpenStack++
      environment. Chris Marino specifically contributed. The privacy issues
      were discussed with Alissa Cooper, who made suggestions.</t>
    </section>
  </middle>
  <back>
    <!-- references split to informative and normative -->
<!--
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
    </references>
-->
    <references title="Informative References">
<!--
      <?rfc include="reference.I-D.gont-opsec-ipv6-eh-filtering" ?>
-->
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2460"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.1984" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2804" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6973" ?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7258" ?>
      <reference anchor="Saltzer">
        <front>
          <title>End-to-end arguments in system design</title>
          <author initials="JH" surname="Saltzer">
            <organization>M.I.T. Laboratory for Computer
            Science</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="DP" surname="Reed">
            <organization>M.I.T. Laboratory for Computer
            Science</organization>
          </author>
          <author initials="DD" surname="Clark">
            <organization>M.I.T. Laboratory for Computer
            Science</organization>
          </author>
          <date month="Nov" year="1984"/>
        </front>
        <seriesInfo name="ACM Transactions on Computer Systems (TOCS)"
                    value="v.2 n.4, p277-288"/>
        <format target="http://mit.edu/Saltzer/www/publications/endtoend/endtoend.pdf"
                type="PDF"/>
      </reference>
    </references>
    <section anchor="log" title="Change Log">
      <t><list style="hanging">
          <t hangText="Initial Version:">September 2014</t>
        </list></t>
    </section>
  </back>
</rfc>
